
<div xml:id="BNCdes" type="foo"><head>Design of the corpus</head>
<p>This section discusses some of the basic design issues underlying
the creation of the BNC. It summarizes the kinds of uses for which the
corpus is intended, and the principles upon which it was created. Some
summary information about the composition of the corpus is also
included. 
</p>

<!-- text class table is in file classtab.xml -->
<div xml:id="BNCpurp" type="bar"><head>Purpose</head> 
<p> The   uses originally  envisaged for the British National Corpus
were set out in a working document called <title>Planned Uses of the
British National Corpus</title> BNCW02 (11 April 91). This document
identified the following as likely application areas for the corpus: 
<list><item>reference book publishing</item>
<item>academic linguistic research</item>
<item>language teaching</item>
<item>artificial intelligence</item>
<item>natural language processing</item>
<item>speech processing</item>
<item>information retrieval</item></list></p>
<p>The  same document identified the following categories of linguistic
information derivable from the corpus:
<list><item>lexical</item>
<item>semantic/pragmatic</item>
<item>syntactic</item>
<item>morphological</item>
<item>graphological/written form/orthographical</item>
</list></p>
<p>In the 15 or more years since that document was published, it has
become apparent that the corpus, and corpus methods in general, have
had a far wider impact than anticipated, notably in the field of
language  teaching. </p>
</div>
<div xml:id="BNCdefn">
<head>General definitions</head> 
<p> The British National Corpus is:
<list>
<item>	 a <hi rend="bold">sample</hi> corpus: composed of text samples
generally no longer than 45,000 words.</item>
<item> a <hi rend="bold">synchronic</hi> corpus: the corpus includes
imaginative texts from 1960, informative texts from 1975.</item>
<item>	a <hi rend="bold">general</hi> corpus: not specifically
restricted to any particular subject field, register or genre.</item>
<item> a <hi rend="bold">monolingual</hi> British English corpus: it
comprises text samples which are substantially the product of speakers
of British English.</item>
<item> a <hi rend="bold">mixed</hi> corpus: it contains examples of
both spoken and written language.</item></list></p>
</div> 

<div xml:id="BNCcompo">
<head>Composition</head> 
<p>There is a broad consensus among the participants in the project and
among corpus linguists that a general-purpose corpus of the English
language would ideally contain a high proportion of spoken language in
relation to written texts. However, it is significantly more expensive
to record and transcribe natural speech than to acquire written text in
computer-readable form. Consequently the spoken component of the BNC
constitutes approximately 10 per cent (10 million words) of the total
and the written component 90 per cent (90 million words). These were
agreed to be realistic targets, given the constraints of time and
budget, yet large enough to yield valuable empirical statistical data
about spoken English. In the BNC sampler,
<!--, or <soCalled>core</soCalled>corpus, -->
a two per cent sample taken from the whole of the BNC, spoken and
written language are present in approximately equal proportions, but
other criteria are not equally balanced.
</p> 
<p>From the start, a decision was taken to select material for
inclusion in the corpus according to an overt methodology, with specific
target quantities of clearly defined types of language. This approach
makes it possible for other researchers and corpus compilers to review,
emulate or adapt concrete design goals. This section outlines these
design considerations, and reports on the final make-up of the BNC.
</p>
<p>This and the other tables in this section show the actual make-up
of the second version of the British National Corpus (the BNC World
Edition) in terms of
<list>
<item>texts : number of distinct samples not exceeding 45,000 words
</item>
<item>S-units: number of <gi>s</gi> elements identified by the CLAWS system
(more or less  equivalent to sentences)
</item>
<item>W-units: number of <gi>w</gi> elements identified by the CLAWS system
(more or less  equivalent to words)
</item> </list></p>
<p>For further explanation of <gi>s</gi> and <gi>w</gi> elements, see
section <ptr target="#cdifcomp"/>.
</p>


<p>The XML Edition of the BNC contains 4049 texts and occupies
(including all markup) 5,228,040 Kb, or about 5.2 Gb. In total, it
comprises just under 100 million orthographic words (specifically,
96986707), but the number of w-units (POS-tagged items) is slightly
higher at 98363783. The tagging distinguishes a further
13614425 punctuation strings, giving a total content count of
110691482 strings. The total number of s-units tagged is about
6 million (6026284). Counts for these and all the other elements
tagged in the corpus are provided in the corpus header. </p>

<p>In the following tables both an absolute count and a percentage are
given for all the counts. The percentage is calculated with reference
to the relevant portion of the corpus, for example, in the table for
    "written text domain", with reference to the total number of w-units
in written texts. Note that punctuation strings are <emph>not</emph> included
in these totals. The reference totals used are given in the first table
below.  </p>



<!--<p>The BNC World Edition contains 4054 texts and occupies (including
SGML markup) 1,508,392 Kbytes, or about 1.5 Gb. In total, it comprises
just over 100 million orthographic words (specifically, 100,467,090),
but the number of w-units (POS-tagged items) is slightly less:
97,619,934. The total number of s-units identified by CLAWS is just
over 6 million (6,053,093). Counts for these and all the other
elements tagged in the corpus are provided below in <ptr
target="#bnctags"/></p>
-->


<!-- <eg><![CDATA[ Texts Kbytes S-units W-units
================================================== Written 3209 77.81
1362074 88.03 5188373 89740544 89.64 Spoken ContGov 762 18.47 100172
6.47 430348 6154248 6.14 Spoken Demog 153 3.70 84952 5.49 612049
4211216 4.20 ]]> </eg> -->

<!--
<table xml:id="alltyp" rend="inline">
<head>Composition of the BNC World Edition</head>
<row>
<cell>Text type</cell>
<cell>Texts</cell>
<cell>Kbytes</cell>
<cell>W-units</cell>
<cell>S-units</cell>
<cell>percent</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>Spoken demographic</cell><cell>153</cell><cell>4206058</cell><cell>4.30</cell><cell>610563</cell><cell>10.08</cell></row>
<row><cell>Spoken context-governed</cell><cell>757</cell><cell>6135671</cell><cell>6.28</cell><cell>428558</cell><cell>7.07</cell></row>
<row><cell>All Spoken</cell><cell>910</cell><cell>10341729</cell><cell>10.58</cell><cell>1039121</cell><cell>17.78</cell></row>
<row><cell>Written books and periodicals</cell><cell>2688</cell><cell>78580018</cell><cell>80.49</cell><cell>4403803</cell><cell>72.75</cell></row>
<row><cell>Written-to-be-spoken</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>1324480</cell><cell>1.35</cell><cell>120153</cell><cell>1.98</cell></row>
<row><cell>Written miscellaneous</cell><cell>421</cell><cell>7373707</cell><cell>7.55</cell><cell>490016</cell><cell>8.09</cell></row>
<row><cell>All Written</cell><cell>3144</cell><cell>87278205</cell><cell>89.39</cell><cell>5013972</cell><cell>82.82</cell></row>
</table>
-->

<table xml:id="alltyp" rend="center">
<head>Text type</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Spoken demographic</cell><cell>153</cell><cell>4233955</cell><cell>4.30</cell><cell>610557</cell><cell>10.13</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Spoken context-governed</cell><cell>755</cell><cell>6175896</cell><cell>6.27</cell><cell>427523</cell><cell>7.09</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Written books and periodicals</cell><cell>2685</cell><cell>79238146</cell><cell>80.55</cell><cell>4395581</cell><cell>72.94</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Written-to-be-spoken</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>1278618</cell><cell>1.29</cell><cell>104665</cell><cell>1.73</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Written miscellaneous</cell><cell>421</cell><cell>7437168</cell><cell>7.56</cell><cell>487958</cell><cell>8.09</cell></row>
</table>



<p>All texts are also classified according to their date of
production. For spoken texts, the date was that of the recording. For
written texts, the date used for classification was the date of
publication of the source edition used, for the most part; in
the case of imaginative works, however, the date of first publication
of the work was used. Informative texts were selected only from 1975 onwards,
imaginative ones from 1960, reflecting their longer <q>shelf-life</q>,
though most (75 per cent ) of the latter were published no earlier
than 1975.  <!--<eg><![CDATA[ Texts Kbytes S-units W-units =========
============ ======== ============== 1960-1974 53 1.65 30598 2.24
133217 2036939 2.26 1975-1993 2596 80.89 1213487 89.09 4626639
80077473 89.23 Unclassified 560 17.45 117989 8.66 428517 7626132 8.49
]]> </eg>-->
 
<table xml:id="alltim" rend="center">
<head>Publication date</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>162</cell><cell>1831585</cell><cell>1.86</cell><cell>126416</cell><cell>2.09</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">1960-1974</cell><cell>46</cell><cell>1718449</cell><cell>1.74</cell><cell>119510</cell><cell>1.98</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">1975-1984</cell><cell>169</cell><cell>4730889</cell><cell>4.80</cell><cell>257962</cell><cell>4.28</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">1985-1993</cell><cell>3672</cell><cell>90082860</cell><cell>91.58</cell><cell>5522396</cell><cell>91.63</cell></row>
</table>

<!--<table xml:id="alltim" rend="inline">
<head>Date of production</head>
<row><cell>Creation date</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>162</cell><cell>1814051</cell><cell>1.85</cell><cell>127132</cell><cell>2.10</cell></row>
<row><cell>Before 1974</cell><cell>47</cell><cell>1741624</cell><cell>1.78</cell><cell>121323</cell><cell>2.00</cell></row>
<row><cell>1974 to 1983</cell><cell>156</cell><cell>4621950</cell><cell>4.73</cell><cell>255057</cell><cell>4.21</cell></row>
<row><cell>1984 to 1994</cell><cell>3689</cell><cell>89442309</cell><cell>91.62</cell><cell>5549581</cell><cell>91.68</cell></row>
</table>
-->

</p>
<p>Spoken and written components of the corpus are discussed separately in
the next two sections.</p></div>



<div xml:id="wrides"><head>Design of the written component</head> 

<div><head>Sampling basis: production and reception</head> 

<p>While it is sometimes useful to distinguish in theory between
language which is <term>received</term> (read and heard) and that which
is <term>produced</term> (written and spoken), it was agreed that the
selection of samples for a general-purpose corpus must take account of
both perspectives.</p>
<p>Text that is published in the form of books, magazines, etc., is
not representative of the totality of written language that is produced,
as writing for publication is a comparatively specialized activity in
which few people engage. However, it is much more representative of
written language that is received, and is also easier to obtain in
useful quantities, and thus forms the greater part of the written
component of the corpus.</p>
<p>There was no single source of information about published material
that could provide a satisfactory basis for a sampling frame, but a
combination of various sources furnished useful information about the
totality of written text produced and, particularly, received, some
sources being more significant than others. They are principally
statistics about books and periodicals that are published, bought or
borrowed.</p>
<p>Catalogues of <hi>books published per annum</hi> tell us something
about production but little about reception as many books are published
but hardly read. 
</p>
<p>A list of <hi>books in print</hi> provides somewhat more
information about reception as time will weed out the books that nobody
bought (or read): such a list will contain a higher proportion of books
that have continued to find a readership.
</p>
<p>The books that have the widest reception are presumably those that
figure in <hi>bestseller lists,</hi> particularly <hi>prize
winners</hi> of competitions such as the Booker or Whitbread. Such
works were certainly candidates for inclusion in the corpus, but the
statistics of book-buying are such that very few texts achieve high
sales while a vast number sell only a few or in modest numbers. If
texts had been selected in strict arithmetical proportion to their
sales, their range would have been severely limited. However, where a
text from one particular subject domain was required, it was
appropriate to prefer a book which had achieved high sales to one
which had not. </p> 

<p><hi>Library lending statistics,</hi> where these are available,
also indicate which books enjoy a wide reception and, like lists of
books in print, show which books <emph>continue</emph> to be read.
</p>

<p>Similar observations hold for magazines and periodicals. lists of
<hi>current magazines and periodicals</hi> are similar to catalogues of
published books, but perhaps more informative about language reception,
as it may be that periodicals are bought and read by a wider
cross-section of the community than books. Also, a periodical that fails
to find a readership will not continue to be published for long.
</p>
<p><hi>Periodical circulation figures</hi> have to be treated with the
same caution as bestseller lists, as a few titles dominate the market
with a very high circulation. To concentrate too exclusively on these
would reduce the range of text types in the corpus and make contrastive
analysis difficult.
</p>
<p>Published written texts were selected partly at
random from Whitaker's <title>Books in Print</title> for 1992 and
partly systematically, according to the selection features outlined in
section <ptr target="#SEL"/> below.
</p>
<p>Available sources are concerned almost exclusively with published
books and periodicals. It is much more difficult to obtain data
concerning the production or reception of unpublished writing. Intuitive
estimates were therefore made in order to establish some guidelines for
text sampling in the latter area.
</p></div>
<div xml:id="SEL"><head>Selection features </head> 
<p>Texts were chosen for inclusion according to three
<term>selection features</term>: domain (subject field), time (within
certain dates) and medium (book, periodical, etc.). 
</p>
<p>The purpose of these selection features was to ensure that the
corpus contained a broad range of different language styles, for two
reasons. The first was so that the corpus could be regarded as a
microcosm of current British English in its entirety, not just of
particular types. The second was so that different types of text could
be compared and contrasted with each other.
</p>
<div type="zxz"><head>Selection Procedure</head>
<p>Each selection feature was divided into classes (e.g. <q>Medium</q>
into books, periodicals, unpublished etc.; <q>Domain</q> into
imaginative,  informative, etc.) and target percentages were set for
each class. These percentages are quite independent of each other: there
was no attempt, for example, to make 25 per cent  of the selected
periodicals imaginative.
</p>
<p>The design proposed that seventy-five per cent of the samples be drawn from
informative texts, and the remaining 25 per cent from imaginative texts.
It further proposed that titles be taken from a variety of media, in the following
proportions: 60 per cent from books, 30 per cent from periodicals, 10
per cent from miscellaneous sources (published, unpublished, and written
to be spoken). </p>
<p>Half of the books in the <q>Books and Periodicals</q> class were
selected at random from Whitaker's <title>Books in Print 1992</title>.
This was to provide a control group to validate the categories used in
the other method of selection: the random selection disregarded Domain
and Time, but texts selected by this method were classified according to
these other features after selection. </p>
</div>
<div><head>Sample size and method</head> 
<p>For books, a target sample size of 40,000 words was chosen.  No
extract included in the corpus exceeds 45,000 words. For the most
part, texts which in their entirety were shorter than 40,000 words
were further reduced by ten per cent for copyright reasons; a few
texts longer than the target size were however included in their
entirety.  Text samples normally consist of a continuous stretch of
discourse from within the whole. A convenient breakpoint (e.g. the end
of a section or chapter) was chosen as far as possible to begin and
end the sample so that high-level discourse units were not
fragmented. Where possible, no more than one sample was taken from any
one text; for newspaper texts and large encyclopaedic works, no sample
greater than 40,000 words was taken. Samples were taken randomly from
the beginning, middle or end of longer texts. (In cases where a
publication included essays or articles by a variety of authors of
different nationalities, the work of non-UK authors was omitted.)
</p>
<p>Some types of written material are composite in structure: that is,
the physical object in written form is composed of more than one text
unit. Important examples are issues of a newspaper or magazine which,
though editorially shaped as a document, contain discrete texts, each
with its specific authorship, stylistic characteristics, register and
domain. The BNC attempts to separate these discrete texts where
appropriate and to classify them individually according to the selection
and classification features. As far as possible, the individual stories
in one issue of a newspaper were grouped according to domain, for
example as <q>Business</q> articles, <q>Leisure</q> articles, etc.</p>
<p>The following subsections discuss each selection criterion, and
indicate the actual numbers of words in each category included.
</p></div>

<div ><head>Domain</head> 

<p>Classification according to subject field seems hardly appropriate
to texts which are fictional or which are generally perceived to be
literary or creative. Consequently, these texts are all labelled
<term>imaginative</term> and are not assigned to particular subject
areas. All other texts are treated as <term>informative</term> and are
assigned to one of the eight domains listed below.

<!-- <eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Imaginative          625 19.47  301422 22.12   1580771  19664309 21.91
Arts                 259  8.07  109923  8.07    369762   7253846  8.08
Belief and thought   146  4.54   45472  3.33    154628   3053672  3.40
Commerce             284  8.85  108150  7.94    374830   7118321  7.93
Leisure              374 11.65  151946 11.15    588010   9990080 11.13
Natural science      144  4.48   57075  4.19    181005   3752659  4.18
Applied science      364 11.34  112264  8.24    368723   7369290  8.21
Social science       510 15.89  201313 14.77    661897  13290441 14.80
World affairs        453 14.11  246718 18.11    764867  16507399 18.39
Unclassified          50  1.55   27791  2.04    143880   1740527  1.93
]]></eg> 
-->
<table xml:id="wridom" rend="center">
<head>Written Domain</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Imaginative</cell><cell>476</cell><cell>16496420</cell><cell>18.75</cell><cell>1352150</cell><cell>27.10</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Informative: natural &amp; pure science</cell><cell>146</cell><cell>3821902</cell><cell>4.34</cell><cell>183384</cell><cell>3.67</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Informative: applied science</cell><cell>370</cell><cell>7174152</cell><cell>8.15</cell><cell>356662</cell><cell>7.15</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Informative: social science</cell><cell>526</cell><cell>14025537</cell><cell>15.94</cell><cell>698218</cell><cell>13.99</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Informative: world affairs</cell><cell>483</cell><cell>17244534</cell><cell>19.60</cell><cell>798503</cell><cell>16.00</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Informative: commerce &amp; finance</cell><cell>295</cell><cell>7341163</cell><cell>8.34</cell><cell>382374</cell><cell>7.66</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Informative: arts</cell><cell>261</cell><cell>6574857</cell><cell>7.47</cell><cell>321140</cell><cell>6.43</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Informative: belief &amp; thought</cell><cell>146</cell><cell>3037533</cell><cell>3.45</cell><cell>151283</cell><cell>3.03</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Informative: leisure</cell><cell>438</cell><cell>12237834</cell><cell>13.91</cell><cell>744490</cell><cell>14.92</cell></row>
</table>

<!--
<table xml:id="wridom" rend="inline">
<head>Written domain</head>
<row><cell>Domain</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Applied science</cell><cell>370</cell><cell>7104635</cell><cell>8.14</cell><cell>357067</cell><cell>7.12</cell></row>
<row><cell>Arts</cell><cell>261</cell><cell>6520634</cell><cell>7.47</cell><cell>321442</cell><cell>6.41</cell></row>
<row><cell>Belief and thought</cell><cell>146</cell><cell>3007244</cell><cell>3.44</cell><cell>151418</cell><cell>3.01</cell></row>
<row><cell>Commerce and finance</cell><cell>295</cell><cell>7257542</cell><cell>8.31</cell><cell>382717</cell><cell>7.63</cell></row>
<row><cell>Imaginative</cell><cell>477</cell><cell>16377726</cell><cell>18.76</cell><cell>1356458</cell><cell>27.05</cell></row>
<row><cell>Leisure</cell><cell>438</cell><cell>12187946</cell><cell>13.96</cell><cell>760722</cell><cell>15.17</cell></row>
<row><cell>Natural and pure science</cell><cell>146</cell><cell>3784273</cell><cell>4.33</cell><cell>183466</cell><cell>3.65</cell></row>
<row><cell>Social science</cell><cell>527</cell><cell>13906182</cell><cell>15.93</cell><cell>700122</cell><cell>13.96</cell></row>
<row><cell>World affairs</cell><cell>484</cell><cell>17132023</cell><cell>19.62</cell><cell>800560</cell><cell>15.96</cell></row>
</table>
-->

</p>
<p>The evidence from catalogues of books and periodicals suggests that
imaginative texts account for significantly less than 25 per cent  of
published output, and unpublished reports, correspondence, reference
works and so on would seem to add further to the bulk of informative
text which is produced and consumed. However, the overall distribution
between informative and imaginative text samples is set to reflect the
influential cultural role of literature and creative writing. The target
percentages for the eight informative domains were arrived at by
consensus within the project, based loosely upon the pattern of book
publishing in the UK during the past 20 years or so, as reflected in the
categorized figures for new publications that appear annually in
Whitaker's <title>Book list</title>.</p>
</div>
<div><head>Medium</head>
<p>This categorisation is broad, since a detailed taxonomy or feature
classification of text medium could have led to such a proliferation of
subcategories as to make it impossible for the BNC adequately to
represent all of them. The labels used here are intended to be
comprehensive in the sense that any text can be assigned with reasonable
confidence to these macro categories. The labels we have adopted
represent the highest levels of a fuller taxonomy of text medium. 

<table xml:id="wrimed" rend="center">
<head>Written Medium</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Book</cell><cell>1411</cell><cell>50293803</cell><cell>57.18</cell><cell>2887523</cell><cell>57.88</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Periodical</cell><cell>1208</cell><cell>28609494</cell><cell>32.52</cell><cell>1487644</cell><cell>29.82</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Miscellaneous published</cell><cell>238</cell><cell>4233135</cell><cell>4.81</cell><cell>287700</cell><cell>5.76</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Miscellaneous unpublished</cell><cell>249</cell><cell>3538882</cell><cell>4.02</cell><cell>220672</cell><cell>4.42</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">To-be-spoken</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>1278618</cell><cell>1.45</cell><cell>104665</cell><cell>2.09</cell></row>
</table>

<!--
<table xml:id="wrimed" rend="inline">
<head>Written medium</head>
<row><cell>Medium</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Book</cell><cell>1414</cell><cell>49891770</cell><cell>57.16</cell><cell>2895652</cell><cell>57.75</cell></row>
<row><cell>Periodical</cell><cell>1208</cell><cell>28356005</cell><cell>32.48</cell><cell>1487725</cell><cell>29.67</cell></row>
<row><cell>Published miscellanea </cell><cell>238</cell><cell>4197450</cell><cell>4.80</cell><cell>288004</cell><cell>5.74</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unpublished miscellanea </cell><cell>249</cell><cell>3508500</cell><cell>4.01</cell><cell>222438</cell><cell>4.43</cell></row>
<row><cell>To-be-spoken</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>1324480</cell><cell>1.51</cell><cell>120153</cell><cell>2.39</cell></row>
</table>
-->
<!--
<eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Book                1488 46.36  789896 57.99   3085865  52574506 58.58
Periodical          1167 36.36  425434 31.23   1459694  27897931 31.08
Misc. published      181  5.64   62262  4.57    272431   3936637  4.38
Misc. unpublished    245  7.63   56447  4.14    226174   3595620  4.00
To-be-spoken          49  1.52   22188  1.62    122453   1370870  1.52
Unclassified          79  2.46    5847  0.42     21756    364980  0.40
]]></eg>-->

</p>
<p>The <soCalled>Miscellaneous published</soCalled> category includes
brochures, leaflets, manuals, advertisements. The
<soCalled>Miscellaneous unpublished</soCalled> category includes
letters, memos, reports, minutes, essays. The
<soCalled>written-to-be-spoken</soCalled> category includes scripted television
material, play scripts etc.</p> </div></div>
<div>
<head>Descriptive features</head>
<p>Written texts may be further classified according to sets of
<term>descriptive features</term>. These features <emph>describe</emph>
the sample texts; they did not determine their selection. This
information is recorded to allow more delicate contrastive analysis of
particular sets of texts. As a simple example, the gross division into
two time periods in the selection features can, of course, be refined
and subcorpora defined over the BNC for more specific dates. However,
the relative sizes of such subcorpora are undefined by the BNC design
specification.
</p> 
<p>These descriptive features were monitored during the course of the
data gathering, and text selection, in cases where a free choice of
texts was available, took account of the relative balance of these
features.  Thus although no relative proportions were defined  for
different target age groups (for example), we ensured that the corpus
does contain texts intended for children as well as for adults.</p>  
<p>The following tables summarize the results for the first release of
the corpus. Note that many texts remain unclassified. 
</p>
<div><head>Author information</head> 

<p>Information about authors of written texts was included only where
it was readily available, for example from the dust-wrapper of a book.
Consequently, the coverage of such information is very patchy. The
authorship of a written text was characterized as
<soCalled>corporate</soCalled> where it was produced by an
organization and no specific author was given, and as
<soCalled>multiple</soCalled> in cases where several authors were
named.  Author sex was classified as <q>mixed</q> where more than one
author of either sex was specified, and <q>unknown</q> where it could
not reliably be determined from the author's name. Note that
<soCalled>author age</soCalled> means the author's age at the time of
creation of the work concerned.
</p>

<p>

<table xml:id="wriaty" rend="center">
<head>Author type</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>211</cell><cell>3786835</cell><cell>4.30</cell><cell>174371</cell><cell>3.49</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Corporate author</cell><cell>347</cell><cell>6497144</cell><cell>7.38</cell><cell>455649</cell><cell>9.13</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Multiple author</cell><cell>1322</cell><cell>34563219</cell><cell>39.29</cell><cell>1810901</cell><cell>36.30</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Sole author</cell><cell>1261</cell><cell>43106734</cell><cell>49.01</cell><cell>2547283</cell><cell>51.06</cell></row>
</table>

<!--
<table xml:id="wriaty" rend="inline">
<head>Type of author</head> 
<row><cell>Author type</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>211</cell><cell>3750668</cell><cell>4.29</cell><cell>175027</cell><cell>3.49</cell></row>
<row><cell>Corporate</cell><cell>347</cell><cell>6497415</cell><cell>7.44</cell><cell>471152</cell><cell>9.39</cell></row>
<row><cell>Multiple</cell><cell>1323</cell><cell>34284025</cell><cell>39.28</cell><cell>1813636</cell><cell>36.17</cell></row>
<row><cell>Sole</cell><cell>1263</cell><cell>42746097</cell><cell>48.97</cell><cell>2554157</cell><cell>50.94</cell></row>
</table>-->

<!--
<eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Corporate            397 12.37   94395  6.93    382939   5921328  6.59
Multiple            1357 42.28  541876 39.78   1930170  35612151 39.68
Sole                1331 41.47  680653 49.97   2737747  45296858 50.47
Unknown              122  3.80   43810  3.21    131295   2822572  3.14
Unclassified           2  0.06    1340  0.09      6222     87635  0.09
]]></eg>-->
</p> 

<p>

<table xml:id="wriase" rend="center">
<head>Sex of author</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>1573</cell><cell>36161115</cell><cell>41.11</cell><cell>1968162</cell><cell>39.45</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author sex Male</cell><cell>920</cell><cell>30665582</cell><cell>34.86</cell><cell>1671420</cell><cell>33.50</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author sex Female</cell><cell>414</cell><cell>14588260</cell><cell>16.58</cell><cell>967522</cell><cell>19.39</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author sex Mixed</cell><cell>234</cell><cell>6538975</cell><cell>7.43</cell><cell>381100</cell><cell>7.64</cell></row>
</table>

<!--
<table xml:id="wriase" rend="inline">
<head>Author sex</head>
<row><cell>Author sex</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>1573</cell><cell>35825335</cell><cell>41.04</cell><cell>1970482</cell><cell>39.29</cell></row>
<row><cell>Male</cell><cell>922</cell><cell>30434132</cell><cell>34.87</cell><cell>1675236</cell><cell>33.41</cell></row>
<row><cell>Female</cell><cell>415</cell><cell>14480939</cell><cell>16.59</cell><cell>972106</cell><cell>19.38</cell></row>
<row><cell>Mixed</cell><cell>234</cell><cell>6537799</cell><cell>7.49</cell><cell>396148</cell><cell>7.90</cell></row>
</table>
--><!--
<eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Male                 948 29.54  473329 34.75   1762987  31586324 35.19
Female               445 13.86  234167 17.19   1048883  15497994 17.26
Mixed                208  6.48   79248  5.81    278881   5268444  5.87
Unknown              117  3.64   38627  2.83    137804   2594892  2.89
Unclassified        1491 46.46  536703 39.40   1959818  34792890 38.77
]]></eg>-->
 </p>

<p>

<table xml:id="wriaag" rend="center">
<head>Author age-group</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>2518</cell><cell>66000719</cell><cell>75.04</cell><cell>3687586</cell><cell>73.92</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author age 0-14</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>59559</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>3443</cell><cell>0.06</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author age 15-24</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>542578</cell><cell>0.61</cell><cell>29810</cell><cell>0.59</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author age 25-34</cell><cell>66</cell><cell>2267139</cell><cell>2.57</cell><cell>159455</cell><cell>3.19</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author age 35-44</cell><cell>191</cell><cell>6726926</cell><cell>7.64</cell><cell>410143</cell><cell>8.22</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author age 45-59</cell><cell>205</cell><cell>7230714</cell><cell>8.22</cell><cell>410644</cell><cell>8.23</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author age 60+</cell><cell>139</cell><cell>5126297</cell><cell>5.82</cell><cell>287123</cell><cell>5.75</cell></row>
</table>
<!--
<table xml:id="wriag" rend="inline">
<head>Author age group </head>
<row><cell>Author age</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>2519</cell><cell>65457159</cell><cell>74.99</cell><cell>3707600</cell><cell>73.94</cell></row>
<row><cell>0-14</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>59071</cell><cell>0.06</cell><cell>3447</cell><cell>0.06</cell></row>
<row><cell>15-24</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>537251</cell><cell>0.61</cell><cell>29862</cell><cell>0.59</cell></row>
<row><cell>25-34</cell><cell>67</cell><cell>2286936</cell><cell>2.62</cell><cell>163079</cell><cell>3.25</cell></row>
<row><cell>35-44</cell><cell>191</cell><cell>6660606</cell><cell>7.63</cell><cell>410324</cell><cell>8.18</cell></row>
<row><cell>45-59</cell><cell>205</cell><cell>7157985</cell><cell>8.20</cell><cell>410717</cell><cell>8.19</cell></row>
<row><cell>60+</cell><cell>140</cell><cell>5119197</cell><cell>5.86</cell><cell>288943</cell><cell>5.76</cell></row>
</table>
-->

</p>

<!--<eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
0-14                  22  0.68    8846  0.64     40993    581962  0.64
15-24                 15  0.46    6552  0.48     27713    437149  0.48
25-34                 38  1.18   20171  1.48     88760   1325516  1.47
35-44                 80  2.49   42093  3.09    173586   2813226  3.13
45-59                 85  2.64   42506  3.12    170326   2847335  3.17
60+                   70  2.18   36392  2.67    141045   2451519  2.73
Unclassified        2899 90.33 1205514 88.50   4545950  79283837 88.34
]]></eg> </p> -->


<table xml:id="wriad" rend="center">
<head>Domicile</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>2272</cell><cell>57227155</cell><cell>65.06</cell><cell>3133068</cell><cell>62.80</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author domicile UK and Ireland</cell><cell>841</cell><cell>29760000</cell><cell>33.83</cell><cell>1798301</cell><cell>36.05</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author domicile Commonwealth</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>411207</cell><cell>0.46</cell><cell>25759</cell><cell>0.51</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author domicile Continental Europe</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>234402</cell><cell>0.26</cell><cell>12466</cell><cell>0.24</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author domicile USA</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>245604</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>15675</cell><cell>0.31</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Author domicile Elsewhere</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>75564</cell><cell>0.08</cell><cell>2935</cell><cell>0.05</cell></row>
</table>
<!--
<table xml:id="wriado" rend="inline">
<head>Author domicile </head>
<row><cell>Author domicile</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>2273</cell><cell>56750777</cell><cell>65.02</cell><cell>3144578</cell><cell>62.71</cell></row>
<row><cell>UK and Ireland</cell><cell>843</cell><cell>29570097</cell><cell>33.88</cell><cell>1812550</cell><cell>36.14</cell></row>
<row><cell>Commonwealth</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>407076</cell><cell>0.46</cell><cell>25762</cell><cell>0.51</cell></row>
<row><cell>Continental Europe</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>232275</cell><cell>0.26</cell><cell>12469</cell><cell>0.24</cell></row>
<row><cell>USA</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>243177</cell><cell>0.27</cell><cell>15677</cell><cell>0.31</cell></row>
<row><cell>Elsewhere</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>74803</cell><cell>0.08</cell><cell>2936</cell><cell>0.05</cell></row>
</table></p>
-->
<!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Australia              2  0.06    1097  0.08      3436     75251  0.08
Canada                 4  0.12    2051  0.15      7255    140976  0.15
France                 1  0.03     512  0.03      1746     35921  0.04
Germany                1  0.03     564  0.04      1236     38671  0.04
Ireland                6  0.18    3082  0.22     15123    204291  0.22
Italy                  2  0.06    1200  0.08      6276     78988  0.08
Lebanon                1  0.03     563  0.04      1835     38750  0.04
Monaco                 2  0.06    1252  0.09      5896     81588  0.09
New Zealand            2  0.06    1489  0.10      6082     98803  0.11
Portugal               1  0.03     579  0.04      1900     39565  0.04
Singapore              1  0.03     514  0.03      1095     35954  0.04
Switzerland            1  0.03     584  0.04      1268     38315  0.04
UK general           433 13.49  239777 17.60    968125  15921450 17.74
UK North             145  4.51   69178  5.07    271744   4576077  5.09
UK Midlands           51  1.58   27137  1.99    106463   1806221  2.01
UK South             245  7.63  127689  9.37    536153   8464218  9.43
United States          7  0.21    3586  0.26     16332    235761  0.26
Unclassified        2304 71.79  881220 64.69   3236408  57829744 64.44
]]></eg> </p>-->
</div>
<div><head>Target audience</head> 
<p>Some attempt was made to characterize the kind of audience for which
written texts were produced in terms of age, sex and 
<soCalled>level</soCalled> (a subjective assessment of the text's
technicality or difficulty).   The last of these proved very difficult
to assess and was very frequently confused with circulation size or
audience size; for that reason, no figures for it are included here. 
</p>

<table xml:id="wriaud" rend="center">
<head>Audience age</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Child audience</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>903690</cell><cell>1.02</cell><cell>81074</cell><cell>1.62</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Teenager audience</cell><cell>78</cell><cell>1831178</cell><cell>2.08</cell><cell>138098</cell><cell>2.76</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Adult audience</cell><cell>2911</cell><cell>81928776</cell><cell>93.14</cell><cell>4597388</cell><cell>92.16</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Any audience</cell><cell>110</cell><cell>3290288</cell><cell>3.74</cell><cell>171644</cell><cell>3.44</cell></row>
</table>
<!--
<p>
<table xml:id="wriaag" rend="inline">
<head>Target age group</head>
<row><cell>age group</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Child</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>895413</cell><cell>1.02</cell><cell>81085</cell><cell>1.61</cell></row>
<row><cell>Teenager</cell><cell>77</cell><cell>1769940</cell><cell>2.02</cell><cell>135583</cell><cell>2.70</cell></row>
<row><cell>Adult</cell><cell>2915</cell><cell>81345838</cell><cell>93.20</cell><cell>4625633</cell><cell>92.25</cell></row>
<row><cell>Any</cell><cell>110</cell><cell>3267014</cell><cell>3.74</cell><cell>171671</cell><cell>3.42</cell></row>
</table></p>
-->
<!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Child                 45  1.40   15172  1.11     87768    969382  1.08
Teenager              74  2.30   26192  1.92    132041   1702392  1.89
Adult               3086 96.16 1318246 96.78   4958017  86906809 96.84
Unclassified           4  0.12    2464  0.18     10547    161961  0.18
]]></eg></p> -->

<table xml:id="writas" rend="center">
<head>Audience sex</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>706</cell><cell>20271270</cell><cell>23.04</cell><cell>1131254</cell><cell>22.67</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Male audience</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>2396935</cell><cell>2.72</cell><cell>135950</cell><cell>2.72</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Female audience</cell><cell>175</cell><cell>6904137</cell><cell>7.84</cell><cell>503629</cell><cell>10.09</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Mixed audience</cell><cell>2199</cell><cell>58381590</cell><cell>66.37</cell><cell>3217371</cell><cell>64.49</cell></row>
</table>
<!--
<p>
<table xml:id="writas" rend="inline">
<head>Target sex</head>
<row><cell>sex</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>707</cell><cell>20113523</cell><cell>23.04</cell><cell>1135038</cell><cell>22.63</cell></row>
<row><cell>Male</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>2366396</cell><cell>2.71</cell><cell>136564</cell><cell>2.72</cell></row>
<row><cell>Female</cell><cell>176</cell><cell>6882659</cell><cell>7.88</cell><cell>507713</cell><cell>10.12</cell></row>
<row><cell>Mixed</cell><cell>2200</cell><cell>57915627</cell><cell>66.35</cell><cell>3234657</cell><cell>64.51</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
--><!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Male                  63  1.96   36836  2.70    142894   2451934  2.73
Female               167  5.20   94897  6.96    453357   6235502  6.94
Mixed               2034 63.38  825974 60.64   3042506  54523125 60.75
Unclassified         945 29.44  404367 29.68   1549616  26529983 29.56
]]></eg> </p></div>
<div><head>Target audience level</head>

<row><cell>Author type</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>

<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Low                  702 21.87  265807 19.51   1208664  17300636 19.27
Medium              1674 52.16  722938 53.07   2791241  47608524 53.05
high                 824 25.67  369822 27.15   1174730  24598066 27.41
Unclassified           9  0.28    3507  0.25     13738    233318  0.25
]]></eg> </p></div> -->
</div>
<div><head>Miscellaneous classification information</head> 
<p>Written texts were also characterized according to their place of
publication and the type of sampling used.
<!-- , and their perceived "status".  -->
</p>
<p>
<table xml:id="wripp" rend="center">
<head>Publication place</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>690</cell><cell>14718827</cell><cell>16.73</cell><cell>788440</cell><cell>15.80</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">UK (unspecific) publication</cell><cell>263</cell><cell>7163111</cell><cell>8.14</cell><cell>380824</cell><cell>7.63</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Ireland publication</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>570652</cell><cell>0.64</cell><cell>31793</cell><cell>0.63</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">UK: North (north of Mersey-Humber line) publication</cell><cell>191</cell><cell>3781055</cell><cell>4.29</cell><cell>228247</cell><cell>4.57</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">UK: Midlands (north of Bristol Channel-Wash line) publication</cell><cell>93</cell><cell>2590345</cell><cell>2.94</cell><cell>177308</cell><cell>3.55</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">UK: South (south of Bristol Channel-Wash line) publication</cell><cell>1853</cell><cell>58587808</cell><cell>66.61</cell><cell>3360401</cell><cell>67.36</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">United States publication</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>542134</cell><cell>0.61</cell><cell>21191</cell><cell>0.42</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
<!--
<table xml:id="wripp" rend="inline">
<head>Place of publication</head>
<row><cell>Region</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>690</cell><cell>14583761</cell><cell>16.70</cell><cell>790465</cell><cell>15.76</cell></row>
<row><cell>UK (unspecific)</cell><cell>264</cell><cell>7124424</cell><cell>8.16</cell><cell>383046</cell><cell>7.63</cell></row>
<row><cell>Ireland</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>567046</cell><cell>0.64</cell><cell>31825</cell><cell>0.63</cell></row>
<row><cell>UK (North)</cell><cell>192</cell><cell>3778114</cell><cell>4.32</cell><cell>230008</cell><cell>4.58</cell></row>
<row><cell>UK (Midlands)</cell><cell>93</cell><cell>2622554</cell><cell>3.00</cell><cell>192379</cell><cell>3.83</cell></row>
<row><cell>UK (South)</cell><cell>1854</cell><cell>58066891</cell><cell>66.53</cell><cell>3365045</cell><cell>67.11</cell></row>
<row><cell>United States</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>535415</cell><cell>0.61</cell><cell>21204</cell><cell>0.42</cell></row>
</table>
</p>-->
<!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Ireland                7  0.21    1973  0.14      7187    131312  0.14
UK general           295  9.19  123244  9.04    446423   8236486  9.17
UK North             195  6.07   59137  4.34    236104   3854333  4.29
UK Midlands           63  1.96   20960  1.53     77238   1367306  1.52
UK South            1956 60.95  932381 68.45   3638876  61533132 68.56
United States         14  0.43    7899  0.57     21133    535335  0.59
Unclassified         679 21.15  216480 15.89    761412  14082640 15.69
]]></eg> </p></div>
<div><head>Sample type</head>
-->

<p>
<table xml:id="wrisam" rend="center">
<head>Sampling type</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>1583</cell><cell>35551102</cell><cell>40.42</cell><cell>1991798</cell><cell>39.93</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Whole text</cell><cell>270</cell><cell>6524975</cell><cell>7.41</cell><cell>433722</cell><cell>8.69</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Beginning sample</cell><cell>584</cell><cell>21075222</cell><cell>23.96</cell><cell>1119251</cell><cell>22.43</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Middle sample</cell><cell>510</cell><cell>18454807</cell><cell>20.98</cell><cell>1049692</cell><cell>21.04</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">End sample</cell><cell>119</cell><cell>4317326</cell><cell>4.90</cell><cell>253322</cell><cell>5.07</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Composite sample</cell><cell>75</cell><cell>2030500</cell><cell>2.30</cell><cell>140419</cell><cell>2.81</cell></row>
</table>
<!--
<p><table xml:id="wrisam" rend="inline">
<head>Sampling method</head>
<row><cell>Sample type</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>1583</cell><cell>35240809</cell><cell>40.37</cell><cell>1994357</cell><cell>39.77</cell></row>
<row><cell>Whole text</cell><cell>270</cell><cell>6463415</cell><cell>7.40</cell><cell>433833</cell><cell>8.65</cell></row>
<row><cell>Beginning sample</cell><cell>585</cell><cell>20890666</cell><cell>23.93</cell><cell>1121658</cell><cell>22.37</cell></row>
<row><cell>Middle sample</cell><cell>512</cell><cell>18344188</cell><cell>21.01</cell><cell>1055383</cell><cell>21.04</cell></row>
<row><cell>End sample</cell><cell>119</cell><cell>4271138</cell><cell>4.89</cell><cell>253413</cell><cell>5.05</cell></row>
<row><cell>Composite</cell><cell>75</cell><cell>2067989</cell><cell>2.36</cell><cell>155328</cell><cell>3.09</cell></row>
</table>
--><!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Whole text           267  8.32   97239  7.13    430690   6338401  7.06
Beginning sample     599 18.66  319805 23.47   1159389  21419253 23.86
Middle sample        555 17.29  301257 22.11   1180007  20054472 22.34
End sample           127  3.95   69242  5.08    273773   4590518  5.11
Composite             18  0.56    7145  0.52     20354    473753  0.52
Unclassified        1643 51.19  567386 41.65   2124160  36864147 41.07
]]></eg> </p></div>
<div><head>Reception status</head>

<row><cell>Author type</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>

<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Low                  801 24.96  298266 21.89   1037985  19692882 21.94
Medium               903 28.13  487140 35.76   1904635  32120008 35.79
high                1059 33.00  386399 28.36   1608454  25237759 28.12
Unclassified         446 13.89  190269 13.96    637299  12689895 14.14
]]></eg> -->
</p>
<p>In addition to the above, standard bibliographic details such as
author, title, publication details, extent, topic keywords etc. were
recorded for the majority of texts, as further described below (see
<ptr target="#cdifhd"/>).
</p>
</div></div>
<div>
<head>Selection procedures employed 
</head>
<div><head>Books</head>  
<p>Roughly half the titles were randomly selected from available
candidates identified in  Whitaker's <title>Books in Print</title>
(BIP), 1992, by students of Library and Information Studies at Leeds
City University. Each text randomly chosen was accepted only if it
fulfilled certain criteria: it had to be published by a British
publisher, contain sufficient pages of text to make its incorporation 
worthwhile, consist mainly of written text, fall within the
designated time limits, and cost less than a set price. The students
noted the ISBN, author, title and price of each book thus selected; the
final selection weeded out texts by non-UK authors. </p> 
<p>Half of the books having been selected by this method, the
remaining half were selected systematically to make up the target 
percentages in each category. The selection proceeded as follows. </p> 
<div> <head>Bestsellers</head>  
<p>Because of their wide reception, bestsellers were obvious
candidates for selection. The lists used were those that appeared in the
<title>Bookseller</title> at the end of the years 1987 to 1993
inclusive. Some of the books in the lists were rejected, for a variety
of reasons. Obviously books that had already been selected by the random
method were excluded, as were those by non-UK authors. In addition, a
limit of 120,000  words from any one author was imposed, and books
belonging to a domain or category whose quota had already been reached
were not selected. Other bestseller lists were obtained from <title>The
 Guardian,</title> the British Council, and from Blackwells Paperback
Shop.</p>
<p>The titles yielded by this search were mostly in the Imaginative
category.  
</p></div>
<div>
<head>Literary prizes</head>  
<p>The criteria for inclusion were the same as for bestsellers. The
prize winners, together with runners-up and shortlisted titles, were
taken from several sources, principally Anne Strachan,
<title>Prizewinning literature: UK literary award winners,</title>
London, 1989. For 1990 onwards the sources used were: the last issue of
the <title>Bookseller</title> for each year; <title> The Guardian
Index, 1989</title>, entries under the term <q>Literature</q>;
and <title>The Times Index, 1989-,</title> entries under the term
<q>Literature  Awards</q>. </p> 
<p>Literary prizes are in the main awarded to works that fall into the
Imaginative category, but there are some Informative ones also. 
</p></div>
<div>
<head>Library loans</head> 
<p>The source of statistics in this category was the record of loans
under Public Lending Right, kindly provided by Dr J. Parker, the
Registrar. The information comprised lists of the hundred most issued
books and the hundred most issued children's books, in both cases for
the years 1987 to 1993.
</p>
<p>The lists consist almost exclusively of imaginative literature, and
many titles found there also appear in the lists of bestsellers and
prize winners. 
</p></div>
<div><head>Additional texts</head> 
<p>As collection proceeded, monitoring disclosed potential shortfalls
in certain domains. A further selection was therefore made, based on the
<q>Short Loan</q> collections of seven University libraries. (Short
Loan collections typically contain books required for academic courses,
which are consequently in heavy demand.)  
</p></div></div>
<div>
<head>Periodicals and magazines</head> 
<p>Periodicals, magazines and newspapers account for 30 per cent  of
the total text in the corpus. Of these, about 250 titles were issues of
newspapers. These were selected to cover as wide a spectrum of interests
and language as possible. Newspapers were selected to represent as wide
a geographic spread as possible:
<title>The Scotsman</title> and the <title>Belfast Telegraph</title>
are both represented, for example. 
</p></div>
<div><head>Other media</head> 
<p>In addition to samples from books, periodicals, and magazines, the
written part of the corpus contains about seven million words classified as
<q>Miscellaneous Published</q>, <q>Miscellaneous Unpublished</q>, or
as
<q>Written to be spoken</q>.  The distinction between <q>published</q>
and <q>unpublished</q> is not an easy one; the former category largely
contains publicity leaflets, brochures, fact sheets, and similar items,
while the latter has a substantial proportion of school and university
essays, unpublished creative writing or letters, and internal company
memoranda. The <q>written to be spoken</q> material includes  scripted
material, intended to be read aloud such as television news broadcasts; 
transcripts of more informal broadcast materials such as discussions or
phone-ins are included in the spoken part of the corpus. 
</p></div>
<div>
<head>Copyright permissions</head> 
<p>Before a selected text could be included, permissions had to be 
obtained from the copyright owner (publisher, agent, or author).  A
standard Permissions Request was drafted with considerable care, but
some requests were refused, or simply not answered even after prompting,
so that the texts concerned had to be excluded or replaced.
</p></div></div></div>
<div xml:id="spodes"><head>Design of the spoken component</head> 
<p>Lexicographers and linguists have long hoped for corpus evidence
about spoken language, but the practical difficulties of transcribing
sufficiently large quantities of text have prevented the construction of
a spoken corpus of over one million words. The British National Corpus
project undertook to produce 
five to ten million words of orthographically transcribed speech,
covering a wide range of speech variation. A
large proportion of the spoken part of the corpus  over four million words
 comprises spontaneous conversational English. The importance of
conversational dialogue to linguistic study is unquestionable: it is the
dominant component of general language both in terms of language
reception and language production.  
</p>
<p>As with the written part of the corpus, the most important 
considerations in constructing the spoken part were 
sampling and representativeness. The method of transcription was also an
important issue.
</p>
<p>The issues of corpus sampling and representativeness have been
discussed at great length by many corpus linguists.  
With  spoken language there
are no obvious objective measures that can be used to define the target
population or construct a sampling frame. A comprehensive list of text
types can be drawn up but there is no accurate way of estimating the
relative proportions of each text type other than by a priori
linguistically motivated analysis. An alternative approach, one well
known to sociological researchers, is <term>demographic sampling</term>,
and this was broadly the approach adopted for approximately half of the
spoken part of the corpus.  The sampling frame was defined in terms of
the language production of the population of British English speakers in
the United Kingdom. Representativeness was achieved by sampling a spread
of language producers in terms of age, gender, social group, and region,
and recording their language output over a set period of time.  
</p>
<p>We recognised, however, that many types of spoken text are produced
only rarely in comparison with the total output of all <q>speech
producers</q>: for example, broadcast interviews, lectures, legal
proceedings, and other texts produced in situations where 
broadly speaking  there are few producers and many receivers. A
corpus constituted solely on the demographic model would thus omit
important spoken text types. Consequently, the demographic component of
the corpus was complemented with a separate text typology intended to
cover the full range of linguistic variation found in spoken language;
this is termed the <term>context-governed</term> part of the corpus. 
</p>
<div>
<head>The demographically sampled part of the corpus</head> 
<p>The approach adopted uses demographic parameters to sample the
population of British English speakers in the United Kingdom.
Established random location sampling procedures were used to select
individual members of the population by personal interview from across
the country taking into account age, gender, and social group. Selected
individuals used a portable tape recorder to record their own speech and
the speech of people they conversed with over a period of up to a week.
In this way a unique record of the language people use in everyday
conversation was constructed.
</p>
<div><head>Sampling procedure</head> 
<p>124 adults (aged 15+) were recruited from across the United
Kingdom.  Recruits were of both sexes and from all age groups and social
classes. The intention was, as far as possible, to recruit equal numbers
of men and women, equal numbers from each of the six age groups, and
equal numbers from each of four social classes. 
</p>
<p>Additional recordings were gathered for the BNC as part of the
University of Bergen COLT Teenager Language Project. This project used
the same recording methods and transcription scheme as the BNC, but
selected only respondents aged 16 or below.
</p>
<p>The tables below give figures for the amount of transcribed
material collected by each respondent, classified by their age, 
class, and sex.
</p>
<p>

<table xml:id="sdeage" rend="center">
<head>Age-group</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Respondent Age 0-14</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>267005</cell><cell>6.30</cell><cell>41036</cell><cell>6.72</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Respondent Age 15-24</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>665358</cell><cell>15.71</cell><cell>97993</cell><cell>16.04</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Respondent Age 25-34</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>853832</cell><cell>20.16</cell><cell>121752</cell><cell>19.94</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Respondent Age 35-44</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>845153</cell><cell>19.96</cell><cell>126690</cell><cell>20.74</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Respondent Age 45-59</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>963483</cell><cell>22.75</cell><cell>136530</cell><cell>22.36</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Respondent Age 60+</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>639124</cell><cell>15.09</cell><cell>86556</cell><cell>14.17</cell></row>
</table>
<!--
<table xml:id="sdeage" rend="inline">
<head>Age group of demographic respondent</head>
<row><cell>Age group</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>0-14</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>265382</cell><cell>6.30</cell><cell>41035</cell><cell>6.72</cell></row>
<row><cell>15-24</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>660847</cell><cell>15.71</cell><cell>97994</cell><cell>16.04</cell></row>
<row><cell>25-34</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>848162</cell><cell>20.16</cell><cell>121750</cell><cell>19.94</cell></row>
<row><cell>35-44</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>839622</cell><cell>19.96</cell><cell>126688</cell><cell>20.74</cell></row>
<row><cell>45-59</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>957382</cell><cell>22.76</cell><cell>136540</cell><cell>22.36</cell></row>
<row><cell>60+</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>634663</cell><cell>15.08</cell><cell>86556</cell><cell>14.17</cell></row>
</table>-->
</p>
<!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
0-14                  26 16.99    5369  6.32     41113    265716  6.30
15-24                 36 23.52   13848 16.30     99510    668947 15.88
25-34                 29 18.95   16817 19.79    121717    847236 20.11
35-44                 22 14.37   17158 20.19    126665    839026 19.92
45-59                 20 13.07   19142 22.53    136506    956474 22.71
60+                   20 13.07   12618 14.85     86538    633817 15.05
]]></eg> 
-->

<p>
<table xml:id="sdecla" rend="center">
<head>Social class</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>37622</cell><cell>0.88</cell><cell>5340</cell><cell>0.87</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">AB respondent</cell><cell>59</cell><cell>1372933</cell><cell>32.42</cell><cell>197795</cell><cell>32.39</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">C1 respondent</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>1104279</cell><cell>26.08</cell><cell>169387</cell><cell>27.74</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">C2 respondent</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>1087808</cell><cell>25.69</cell><cell>144876</cell><cell>23.72</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">DE respondent</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>631313</cell><cell>14.91</cell><cell>93159</cell><cell>15.25</cell></row>
</table>
<!--
<table xml:id="sdecla" rend="inline">
<head>Social class of demographic respondent</head>

<row><cell>Social class</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>37363</cell><cell>0.88</cell><cell>5339</cell><cell>0.87</cell></row>
<row><cell>AB</cell><cell>59</cell><cell>1363571</cell><cell>32.41</cell><cell>197804</cell><cell>32.39</cell></row>
<row><cell>C1</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>1097023</cell><cell>26.08</cell><cell>169384</cell><cell>27.74</cell></row>
<row><cell>C2</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>1080654</cell><cell>25.69</cell><cell>144877</cell><cell>23.72</cell></row>
<row><cell>DE</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>627447</cell><cell>14.91</cell><cell>93159</cell><cell>15.25</cell></row>
</table>
-->
</p>
<!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
AB                    59 38.56   27612 32.50    199297   1370589 32.54
C1                    36 23.52   22951 27.01    169349   1096111 26.02
C2                    31 20.26   20943 24.65    144848   1079828 25.64
DE                    20 13.07   12689 14.93     93127    626871 14.88
Unclassified           7  4.57     757  0.89      5428     37817  0.89
]]></eg> </p>-->

<table xml:id="sdesex" rend="center">
<head>Sex</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>16245</cell><cell>0.38</cell><cell>2407</cell><cell>0.39</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Male respondent</cell><cell>73</cell><cell>1742222</cell><cell>41.14</cell><cell>248241</cell><cell>40.65</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Female respondent</cell><cell>75</cell><cell>2475488</cell><cell>58.46</cell><cell>359909</cell><cell>58.94</cell></row>
</table>
<!--
<p><table xml:id="sdesex" rend="inline">
<head>Sex of demographic respondent</head><row>
<cell>Sex</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>16151</cell><cell>0.38</cell><cell>2407</cell><cell>0.39</cell></row>
<row><cell>Male</cell><cell>73</cell><cell>1730592</cell><cell>41.14</cell><cell>248247</cell><cell>40.65</cell></row>
<row><cell>Female</cell><cell>75</cell><cell>2459315</cell><cell>58.47</cell><cell>359909</cell><cell>58.94</cell></row>
</table></p>
--><!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Male                  73 47.71   35065 41.27    248843   1732731 41.14
Female                75 49.01   49545 58.32    360802   2462339 58.47
Unclassified           5  3.26     342  0.40      2404     16146  0.38
]]>
</eg>  </p>-->
<p>Recruits who agreed to take part in the project were asked to
record all of their conversations over a two to seven day period. The
number of days varied depending on how many conversations each recruit
was involved in and was prepared to record. Results indicated that most
people recorded nearly all of their conversations, and that the limiting
factor was usually the number of conversations a person had per day. 
The placement day was varied, and recruits were asked to record on the
day after placement and on any other day or days of the week.  In this
way a broad spread of days of the week including weekdays and weekends
was achieved. A conversation log allowed recruits to enter details of
every conversation recorded, and included date, time and setting, and
brief details of other participants. 
</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Recording procedure</head> 
<p>All conversations were recorded as unobtrusively as possible, so
that the material gathered approximated closely to natural, spontaneous
speech. In many cases the only person aware that the conversation was
being taped was the person carrying the recorder. Although an initial
unnaturalness on the part of the recruit was not uncommon this soon
seemed to disappear. Similarly, where non-intrusive recording was not
possible, for example at a family gathering where everyone is aware they
are being recorded, the same initial period of unease sometimes
occurred, but in our experience again vanished quickly. The guarantee of
confidentiality and complete anonymity (all references to full names and
addresses have been removed from the corpus and the log), and the fact
that there was an intermediary between those being recorded and those
listening to the recordings certainly helped. </p> 
<p>For each conversational exchange the person carrying the recorder
told all participants they had been recorded and explained why. Whenever
possible this happened after the conversation had taken place. If any
participant was unhappy about being recorded the recording was erased.
During the project  around 700 hours of recordings were gathered.
</p> 
</div>
<div><head>Sample size</head> 
<p>The number of people recruited may seem small in comparison to some
demographic studies of the population of the United Kingdom.  As with
any sampling method, some  compromise between what was theoretically
desirable and what was feasible within the constraints of the BNC
project had to be made. There is no doubt that recruiting 1000 people
would have given greater statistical validity but the practical
difficulties and cost implications of recruiting 1000 people and
transcribing 50100 million words of speech made this impossible.
Given that we were not attempting to represent the complete range of age
and social groups within each region we considered a sample size between
100 and 130 would  be adequate. The
total number of participants in all conversations was well in excess of
a thousand. 
</p></div>
<div><head>Piloting the demographic sampling approach</head> 
<p>Because this approach to spoken corpus sampling had to our
knowledge never previously been attempted a detailed piloting project
was carried out to investigate:
<list><item>the likelihood that enough material would be obtained from a
sample of around 100 respondents
</item>
<item>any problems that might be encountered during the recruitment and
collection stages
</item>
<item>any problems or difficulties experienced by recruits during
taping or with logging details of conversations and participants
</item>
<item>any areas where the documentation designed for the project could
be improved
</item>
<item>whether the recording quality under a wide range of conditions
would be good enough for accurate transcription
</item>
<item>whether the predicted throughput rates for tape editing,
transcription and checking were accurate.
</item></list></p>
<p>The results of the pilot generally confirmed predictions and allowed
some procedures to be refined for the full project. 
</p></div></div>
<div><head>The context-governed part of the corpus</head> 
<p>As mentioned above, the spoken texts in the demographic part of
the corpus consists mainly of conversational English. A complementary
approach was developed to create what is termed the
<term>context-governed</term> part of the corpus. As in other spoken
corpora, the range of text types was selected according to <foreign>a
priori</foreign> linguistically motivated categories. At the top layer
of the typology is a division into four equal-sized contextually based
categories: educational, business, public/institutional, and leisure.
Each is divided into the subcategories monologue (40 per cent) and
dialogue (60 per cent). Each monologue subcategory therefore totals 10
per cent of the context-governed part of the corpus, and each dialogue
subcategory 15 per cent.
</p>
<p>Within each subcategory a range of text types was defined. This
range was not fixed, and the design was
flexible enough to allow the inclusion of additional text types. The
sampling methodology was different for each text type but the overall
aim was to achieve a balanced selection within each, taking into account
such features as region, level, gender of speakers, and topic. Other
features, such as purpose, were applied on the basis of <foreign>post
hoc</foreign> judgements. 
<!--
The channels <q>broadcast</q> and <q>telephone</q> were applied to
appropriate text types.</p> -->
</p>
<div>
<head>Sampling procedure</head> 
<p>For the most part, a variety of text types were sampled within three
geographic  regions. However, 
some text types,
such as parliamentary proceedings, and most broadcast categories, apply
to the country as a whole and were not regionally sampled. Different
sampling strategies were required for each text type, and these are
outlined below.
</p>
<div>
<head>Educational and informative:</head> 
<list type="gloss"> <label>Lectures, talks, educational demonstrations</label>
<item> Within each sampling area a university (or college of further
education) and a school were selected. A range of lectures and talks was
recorded, varying the topic, level, and speaker gender.</item> 
<label>News commentaries</label>
<item> Regional sampling was not applied, but both national and
regional broadcasting companies were sampled.  The topic, level, and
gender of commentator was varied.</item> 
<label>Classroom interaction</label>
<item> Schools were regionally sampled and the level (generally based
on student age) and topic were varied. Home tutorials were also
included.</item>
</list> 
</div>
<div>
<head>Business:</head> 
<list type="gloss">
<label>Company talks and interviews</label>
<item> Sampling took into account company size, areas of activity, and
gender of speakers.</item> 
<label>Trade union talks</label>
<item> Talks to union members, branch meetings and annual conferences
were all sampled.</item> 
<label>Sales demonstrations</label>
<item> A range of topics was included.</item> 
<label>Business meetings</label>
<item> Companies were selected according to size, area of activity, and
purpose of meeting.</item> 
<label>Consultations</label>
<item> These included medical, legal, business and professional
consultations.</item> 
</list> 
<p>All categories under this heading were regionally sampled.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Public or institutional:</head> 
<list type="gloss"><label>Political speeches</label>
<item> Regional sampling of local politics, plus speeches in both the
House of Commons and the House of Lords (in the latter case,
transcriptions were made by the project, and are not taken from the official
Hansard report).</item> 
<label>Sermons</label>
<item> Different denominations were sampled.</item> 
<label>Public/government talks</label>
<item> Regional sampling of local inquiries and meetings, plus national
issues at different levels.</item> 
<label>Council meetings</label>
<item> Regionally sampled, covering parish, town, district, and county
councils.</item> 
<label>Religious meetings</label>
<item> Includes church meetings, group discussions, and so on. </item> 
<label>Parliamentary proceedings</label>
<item> Sampling of main sessions and committees, House of Commons and
House of Lords.</item>
<label>Legal proceedings</label>
<item>Royal Courts of Justice, and local Magistrates and similar courts
were sampled.
</item></list> </div>
<div>
<head>Leisure:</head> 
<list type="gloss"><label>Speeches</label>
<item> Regionally sampled, covering a variety of occasions and
speakers.</item> 
<label>Sports commentaries</label>
<item> Exclusively broadcast, sampling a variety of sports,
commentators, and TV/radio channels.</item> 
<label>Talks to clubs </label>
<item> Regionally sampled, covering a range of topics and speakers.</item>
<label>Broadcast chat shows and phone-ins</label>
<item> Only those that include a significant amount of unscripted
speech were selected from both television and radio. 
</item> 
<label>Club meetings</label>
<item> Regionally sampled, covering a wide range of clubs.</item></list></div></div>
<div>
<head>Sample size</head> 
<p>Each monologue text type contains up to 200,000 words of text, and
each dialogue text type up to 300,000 words. The length of text units
within each text type vary  for example, news commentaries may
be only a few minutes long (several hundred words), lectures are
typically up to one hour (10,000 words), and some business meetings
and parliamentary proceedings may last for several hours (20,000
words+).  For the context-governed part of the corpus an upper limit
of 10,000 words per text unit was generally imposed, although a few
texts are slightly above this.  </p>
</div>
<div><head>Composition of the spoken component</head> 
<p>A total of 757 texts (6,153,671 words) make up the context-governed
part of the corpus. The following contexts are distinguished: 
<table xml:id="scgdom" rend="center">
<head>Spoken context</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Educational/Informative</cell><cell>169</cell><cell>1646380</cell><cell>26.65</cell><cell>118987</cell><cell>27.83</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Business</cell><cell>129</cell><cell>1282416</cell><cell>20.76</cell><cell>107366</cell><cell>25.11</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Public/Institutional</cell><cell>262</cell><cell>1672658</cell><cell>27.08</cell><cell>96500</cell><cell>22.57</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Leisure</cell><cell>195</cell><cell>1574442</cell><cell>25.49</cell><cell>104670</cell><cell>24.48</cell></row>
</table>

<!--<table xml:id="scgdom" rend="inline">
<head>Context in which spoken text was captured</head>
<row><cell>Context</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Educational/Informative</cell><cell>169</cell><cell>1633303</cell><cell>26.61</cell><cell>119252</cell><cell>27.82</cell></row>
<row><cell>Business</cell><cell>131</cell><cell>1285938</cell><cell>20.95</cell><cell>108101</cell><cell>25.22</cell></row>
<row><cell>Public/Institutional</cell><cell>262</cell><cell>1655263</cell><cell>26.97</cell><cell>96504</cell><cell>22.51</cell></row>
<row><cell>Leisure</cell><cell>195</cell><cell>1561167</cell><cell>25.44</cell><cell>104701</cell><cell>24.43</cell></row>
</table>
-->
</p>
<!--
<eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Educational          144 18.89   21037 21.00    100745   1265318 20.56
Business             136 17.84   22344 22.30    110421   1321844 21.47
Institutional        241 31.62   21878 21.84     77694   1345694 21.86
Leisure              187 24.54   23451 23.41    101207   1459419 23.71
Unclassified          54  7.08   11462 11.44     40281    761973 12.38
]]></eg> </p> -->
<p>In addition, the following classifications are applicable  to  both
demographic and context-governed spoken texts:

<table xml:id="sporeg" rend="center">
<head>Region</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Unknown</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>448458</cell><cell>4.30</cell><cell>27496</cell><cell>2.64</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">South </cell><cell>311</cell><cell>4687877</cell><cell>45.03</cell><cell>457726</cell><cell>44.09</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Midlands</cell><cell>213</cell><cell>2492236</cell><cell>23.94</cell><cell>240306</cell><cell>23.14</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">North</cell><cell>349</cell><cell>2781280</cell><cell>26.71</cell><cell>312552</cell><cell>30.10</cell></row>
</table>
<!--
<table xml:id="sporeg" rend="inline"><head>Region where spoken text captured</head>
<row><cell>Region</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>446584</cell><cell>4.31</cell><cell>27706</cell><cell>2.66</cell></row>
<row><cell>South</cell><cell>312</cell><cell>4658232</cell><cell>45.04</cell><cell>458253</cell><cell>44.10</cell></row>
<row><cell>Midlands</cell><cell>213</cell><cell>2471184</cell><cell>23.89</cell><cell>240320</cell><cell>23.12</cell></row>
<row><cell>North</cell><cell>350</cell><cell>2765729</cell><cell>26.74</cell><cell>312842</cell><cell>30.10</cell></row>
</table>
-->

<!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
South                296 32.34   83425 45.06    461171   4728472 45.61
Midlands             208 22.73   42658 23.04    234095   2418278 23.33
North                334 36.50   49349 26.65    301875   2636312 25.43
Unclassified          77  8.41    9692  5.23     45256    582402  5.61
]]></eg> </p>-->

<table xml:id="spolog" rend="center">
<head>Interaction type</head>
<row role="label"><cell/><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell><cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row><row><cell role="label">Monologue</cell><cell>207</cell><cell>1562017</cell><cell>15.00</cell><cell>92619</cell><cell>8.92</cell></row>
<row><cell role="label">Dialogue</cell><cell>701</cell><cell>8847834</cell><cell>84.99</cell><cell>945461</cell><cell>91.07</cell></row>
</table>

</p>
</div></div></div></div>
<!--
<table xml:id="spolog" rend="inline"><head>Interaction type for spoken text</head>

<row><cell>Interaction type</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Monologue</cell><cell>212</cell><cell>1578614</cell><cell>15.26</cell><cell>94272</cell><cell>9.07</cell></row>
<row><cell>Dialogue</cell><cell>698</cell><cell>8763115</cell><cell>84.73</cell><cell>944849</cell><cell>90.92</cell></row>
</table> -->
<!--
<p><eg><![CDATA[
                         Texts        Kbytes   S-units         W-units
                     =========  ============  ========  ==============
Monologue            218 23.82   30152 16.28    114362   1932225 18.64
Dialogue             672 73.44  144666 78.14    888535   7760753 74.87
Unclassified          25  2.73   10306  5.56     39500    672486  6.48
]]></eg>
-->
